<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SPTR</title>
    <description>Last in, first out</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>The Magic Physics Pixies</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;SPTR.net was for several years, a resource sharing site for physics teachers in Scotland. That role was taken up by Sally over at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.guzledscotland.com/&quot;&gt;Guzled&lt;/a&gt; in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have this week relocated the sptr.net&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:domain&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:domain&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; website to a new home, and removed a lot of the old, dead posts, keeping just a few of particular interest or significance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact us over at cullaloe.net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:domain&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;The sptr.net domain is either not for sale, or you can’t afford it. &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:domain&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2019 22:51:38 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/06/09/magic-physics-pixies/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2019/06/09/magic-physics-pixies/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>SPTR Closes on 1st July 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As previously announced, this site will be ceasing operation at the end of this academic session. On Friday 1st July 2016, the resources will be retired from the site and logins disabled.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 May 2016 18:00:38 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/sptr-closes-on-1st-july-2016/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/sptr-closes-on-1st-july-2016/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Can I get a PGCE in England and then teach in Scotland?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This question comes up sometimes when people hear about the cash incentives offered by the DfES through the Institute of Physics in England. These incentives offer a bounty of up to £30K but they are subject to terms and conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you apply for the bursary, you will be required to make a written commitment to seek a teaching post in England. I know of nobody who has completed PGCE in England, picked up the bounty money and crossed the border. I am not sure that if you reneged on your commitment to teach in England, you would not be required to repay some or all of the bursary. A Scottish PGDE gives you guaranteed entry to the Teacher Induction Scheme that allows you to complete your probation in one year in a state school. There is nothing to prevent you from applying for GTCS registration after a few years teaching in England but be aware, you are likely to still need to complete a probationary period before gaining full registration status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;General observations are that although English PGCEs are every bit as valid as the Scottish PGDE, there are other routes into teaching in England. I believe that even the QTS is being abolished there as part of the academisation of all state schools. The Scottish stance is much more guarded: we insist on fully qualified and registered teachers, even in the independent sector. This is one of the reasons that Scottish qualified teachers are so highly regarded around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(cross-posted from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/groups/8451229&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LinkedIn Teaching Physics in Scotland Group&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 09:53:21 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/can-i-get-a-pgce-in-england-and-then-teach-in-scotland/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/can-i-get-a-pgce-in-england-and-then-teach-in-scotland/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A professional community resource</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2015/06/ALT15Pixies.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignright wp-image-20510 size-medium&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2015/06/ALT15Pixies-300x225.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Thursday last week, I gave a short talk on the background and operation of this site, sptr.net, and the components that make up what I called “a professional community resource”. The event was the Association of Learning Technology Scottish SIG meeting at Glasgow Caledonian University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The presentation slides can be downloaded as a pdf by clicking on the image. You can watch a recording of the event below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/FtrZjzBSgk8?rel=0&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2015 14:22:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/a-professional-community-resource/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/a-professional-community-resource/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Happy birthday, Richard Feynman</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2014/05/rf.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft wp-image-12640 size-full&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2014/05/rf.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;rf&quot; width=&quot;281&quot; height=&quot;249&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Q. What’s this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A. A dead one of these.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 11 May 2014 11:06:39 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/happy-birthday-richard-feynman/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/happy-birthday-richard-feynman/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bragg Medal and Prize</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/07/bragg.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft size-full wp-image-3817&quot; alt=&quot;bragg&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/07/bragg.jpg&quot; width=&quot;127&quot; height=&quot;127&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Bragg Medal and Prize is awarded by the Institute of Physics for “significant contributions to physics education and to widening participation within it”. The 2013 recipient has been announced and is Bob Kibble. From &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iop.org/about/awards/education/bragg/medallists/page_60408.html&quot;&gt;the citation&lt;/a&gt;, Bob receives this award for “…his life-long contributions to the teaching of physics in all phases of education, from primary school to further and higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past four decades, few have made greater contributions to physics education than Bob Kibble. He has substantially widened its congregation, both through his graduates and personally. His enthusiastic teaching and his exceptional leadership in curriculum and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_3818” align=”alignright” width=”173”]&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/07/Bob.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; wp-image-3818 &quot; alt=&quot;Bob Kibble&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/07/Bob-289x300.jpg&quot; width=&quot;173&quot; height=&quot;180&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Bob Kibble[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;resource development and Continuing Professional Development (CPD) have inspired many and enhanced their interest in physics. He has given his time and expertise selflessly to the Association for Science Education, the Institute of Physics, the Royal Society of Edinburgh and the Rank Prize funded Optoelectronics College.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of his former students attribute their success to the firm foundation they received through his teaching. He not only covered the required physics but ensured that they had firm understanding of the concepts involved. In 1997, Bob Kibble transferred his talents to teacher training and has influenced, in similar manner, approximately 300 new physics teachers since then”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all wish Bob hearty congratulations for this thoroughly well deserved recognition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2013 06:20:39 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/bragg-medal-and-prize/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/bragg-medal-and-prize/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>&amp;#8216;Allo, John.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/05/cullaloe_2013-05-09.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot; wp-image-1196 alignleft&quot; style=&quot;margin-left: 2px; margin-right: 2px;&quot; alt=&quot;cullaloe_2013-05-09&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2013/05/cullaloe_2013-05-09.jpg&quot; width=&quot;314&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;On a visit to a school in Edinburgh today, an S3 Intermediate 2 class were making electric motors. One group got their kit working in about 25 minutes (including cutting and stripping wire, winding the armature and fitting the bushes), so entertained themselves by fixing red and blue card on either side of the armature faces, predicting a cool purple colour would be seen when the motor ran.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is, in all its purple glory. Click the image for a full sized version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.blipfoto.com/cullaloe&quot;&gt;As one commentator put it&lt;/a&gt;, “a proper experiment! there is hope for our children after all…”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 May 2013 18:17:32 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/allo-john/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/allo-john/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Electricity is all magic</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2012/05/sefton.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;alignleft  wp-image-98&quot; title=&quot;sefton&quot; src=&quot;http://sptr.net/files/2012/05/sefton.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;239&quot; height=&quot;186&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great dialogue on SPUTNIK recently challenged some of the models and beliefs many of us have about just exactly what happens in a simple electrical circuit when a battery lights a bulb. From Paul Chambers (via a post by Tom Clark), light was shed on the problem (pun intended) by a brilliant paper produced by Ian Sefton of the University of Sydney, called “&lt;strong&gt;Understanding Electricity and Circuits: What the Text Books Don’t Tell You”.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might like to read it yourself - download the pdf &lt;a href=&quot;http://science.uniserve.edu.au/school/curric/stage6/phys/stw2002/sefton.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; data-bitly-type=&quot;bitly_hover_card&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 20 May 2012 05:43:16 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/electricity-is-all-magic/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/electricity-is-all-magic/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
